# Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

## **ELLIS PhD Student in ML**

LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez
Personal WWW & Google Scholar

Me – I'm a '97 Spanish ELLIS PhD Student focused on my 1st year PhD with a strong interest in Algorithmic Fairness using Causality and Graph theory. ELLIS is an Al research network focused on excellence, with 35 units in 15 countries of Europe (Oxford, Cambridge, EPFL, ETH, Max plank, Alicante...). ELLIS has 199 PhD students around Europe with an acceptance rate of <5%, and all of them have joint supervision from 2 different countries.

Research Topic – My current thesis addresses the ethical implications of ML decisions, including concepts such as privacy, transparency, accountability, reliability, autonomy, and fairness, which urgently need to be taken into account in critical decision-making scenarios. In this thesis, (1) we study what data might be the cause of unfairness or what data should look like in a "fair" world (2) fairness in graph data to capture complex data relationships and human-generated data, and (3) go beyond observational data and study the long term effects and feedback loops of these proposed algorithms using causality. Specifically, we first study the influence of each data point in a fairness metric for reducing the bias in ML models using *Data Valuation*. Second, we study *Graph Rewiring* methods that ensure fair graph data, and finally, we use *Causality* to improve these methods going beyond observational data for developing fair robust models. In sum, what data causes unfairness, what data should look in a fair world, and their societal effects.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD Student / Fairness in ML

Dec 2021 — Present

ELLIS Alicante – Institute of Humanity-centric AI (European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems)

- · Researching on Fairness in ML decision making leveraging graph theory, game theory and causality.
- Supervised by Dr. Nuria Oliver (ELLIS), Dr. Manuel Gómez Rodríguez (MPI-SWS) and Dr. Francisco Escolano (UA)
- 6-months exchange at Max Plank Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS), Kaiserslautern, 2023
- More info: [European Lab. for Learning and Intelligent Systems ELLIS] [Research Topic]

### MSc in AI & Data Science

Jan 2020 — Jan 2021

Universitat Oberta de Catalunya

GPA:9.7/10

- Evaluated both Masters and Thesis with Honors
- Thesis supervised by Dr. Baris Kanber from University Collegue of London: Deep Convolutional Autoencoder for denoise T1 brain MRI

#### **BSc in Computer Engeneering**

Sep 2015 — Jun 2019

University of Burgos

GPA:8.9/10

- Evaluated both Bachelors and Thesis with Honors
- Extraordinary award: best student in the promotion.
- Thesis carried out in ADMIRABLE research lab: Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson
- Press coverage: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Staff
ADMIRABLE and DATAHES research labs

Jan 2020 — Aug 2021

University of Burgos, Spain

- European project [2019-1-ES01-KA204-065615] Self-Regulated Learning: SmartArt.
- Behavioural VR data analysis and Platform UBUMLaas
- Academic production shown in *Publications* section (Topic: Network Science and Web mining)

Al Consultant Ernst & Young Aug 2019 — Jan 2020

Madrid, Spain

• Building ML models for RPA integration: Intelligent Automation

Research intern

ADMIRABLE research lab

Dec 2018 — Jun 2019

University of Burgos, Spain

• Research intern with collaboration scholarship. Research in the project *Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson* (BSc Thesis).

# Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

## **ELLIS PhD Student in ML**

LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez
Personal WWW & Google Scholar

#### **PRE PRINTS**

[1] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, Ahmed Begga, Francisco Escolano, and Nuria Oliver. "DiffWire: Inductive Graph Rewiring via the Lovász Bound". arXiv preprint arXiv:2206.07369. 2022. URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.07369.

#### **CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, José Luis Garrido-Labrador, and Alicia Olivares-Gil. "Computer Science doctoral research in Spain. A relational perspective". In: *Actas de la XIX Conferencia de la Asociación Española para la Inteligencia Artificial*. Universidad de Málaga. Málaga, 2021, pp. 667–672. ISBN: 978-84-09-30514-8. URL: https://caepia20-21.uma.es/inicio\_files/caepia20-21-actas.pdf#page702.
- [2] José Luis Garrido-Labrador, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, Virginia Ahedo, César Arnaiz-Rodríguez Adrián García-Osorio, José Ignacio Santos, and José Manuel Galán. "Network analysis of co-participation in thesis examination committees in an academic field in Spain". In: Abstract book of the 14th International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Industrial Management and XXIV Congreso de Ingeniería de Organización. Universidad Carlos III de Madrid. Burgos, 2020. URL: https://eventos.uc3m.es/\_files/\_event/\_43190/\_editorFiles/file/BookOfAbstracts10.pdf.

#### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Alicia Olivares Gil, Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez Sanz, José Luis Garrido Labrador, Virginia Ahedo García, César García Osorio, José Ignacio Santos Martín, José Manuel Galán Ordax, et al. "Mapping the scientific structure of organization and management of enterprises using complex networks". In: International Journal of Production Management and Engineering 10.1 (2022), pp. 65–76. URL: <a href="https://polipapers.upv.es/index.php/IJPME/article/view/16666">https://polipapers.upv.es/index.php/IJPME/article/view/16666</a>.
- [2] Esther Cubo, Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez, Álvar Arnaiz-González, José Francisco Díez-Pastor, Meredith Spindler, Adriana Cardozo, Alvaro Garcia-Bustillo, Zoltan Mari, and Bastiaan R Bloem. "Videoconferencing Software Options for Telemedicine: A Review for Movement Disorder Neurologists". In: *Frontiers in neurology* (2021), p. 1812. URL: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2021.745917/full.
- [3] María Consuelo Sáiz-Manzanares, Ismael Ramos Pérez, Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez, Sandra Rodríguez Arribas, Leandro Almeida, and Caroline Françoise Martin. "Analysis of the learning process through eye tracking technology and feature selection techniques". In: *Applied Sciences* 11.13 (2021), p. 6157. URL: <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/11/13/6157/htm">https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/11/13/6157/htm</a>.

#### **HONORS & AWARDS**

Top 10% Reviewer ICML 2022 [Link]

International Conference on Machine Learning, July 2022

Selected in the top 10% best reviewers in ICML 2022 Conference.

FPU PhD Fellowship (Declined) - FPU20/03687

Spanish Government - Ministry of Universities, Sep 2021

Grants for pre-doctoral contracts in Spanish Universities.

Extraordinary Award of Bachelors in Computer Engineering

Council of the University of Burgos, Dec 2019

Best student the Degree in Computer Engineering of the University of Burgos, among all the students graduated in 18/19. **Prototype Award** [Press coverage: 1, 2, 3]

OTRI (Service for Technology Transfer University of Burgos), Feb 2019

Project awarded: Use of bio-markers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson.

**Undergraduated Research Fellowship** 

University of Burgos, Dec 2018

Assistant research Fellowship in the Civil Engineering department of the University of Burgos, research group ADMIRABLE

Courses with honors

Bachelor's and Master's

8 out of 10 MSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis.

10 BSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis.

## Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

**ELLIS PhD Student in ML** 

LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez
Personal WWW & Google Scholar

#### **TALKS**

A Fairness perspective in algorithmic decision-making [Link1, Link2]

University of Burgos (online), Mar 2022

ELLIS + Qualcomm AI Research: Graph Neural Networks and Human-Centric Machine Learning [Link]

Virtual, Feb 2022

- Moderator and Panel Participant
- Panel: Pim de Haan, Carlos Castillo, Efstatios Gavves and Manuel Gómez Rodríguez

[ELLIS Talks] Fairness in Machine Learning: From introduction to current approaches [Link] *University of Alicante, Jan 2022*Data processing in Advance Learning Technology [Link] Self-Regulated Learning in SmartArt Learning conference, Jul 2021

#### SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY SERVICES

#### Reviewer

[External reviewer] Journal of Complexity 2022.

[External reviewer] ICML 2022 - International Conference on Machine Learning - **Top 10% Outstanding Reviewer** [PC member] ECML-PKDD 2022 - European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (x4 papers)

[External reviewer] The Web Conference 2022 (WWW'22), ACM, New York.

[PC member] IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems 2022.

#### Scientific organization

Head of organization of ELLIS Doctoral Symposium 2022

Head of organization of ELLIS HCML Reading Group: guest sessions and round tables Moderator of Qualcomm+ELLIS Reading Group Session about GNN+HCML

Round table: Pim de Haan, Carlos Castillo, Efstatios Gavves and Manuel Gómez Rodríguez

Volunteer at NeurIPS Workshop "Human-Centered AI"

Alicante, Sep 2022 bi-weekly sessions Online, Feb 2022

Virtual, Dec 2021

#### **Open Source software**

Open source code from both BSc and MSc final projects

Occasional collaborator in Lightly AI PyTorch-based library for Self-Supervised Learing. Main contributor of *Lightly version* 1.1.2 More open source codes in GitHub: applications, experiments and data analysis

### **ACTIVITIES**

Final stage II Premios Semilla Empresarial (Business Seed Awards)[Project]
3rd place in Innovation Contest Spin Up CyL by Junior Achievement Foundation Spain [Project]

Mar 2017 Jan 2017

#### **SKILLS**

Languages and libs More interests Communication Python, R, Tensorflow, PyTorch, PyGeometric

Mathematical optimization, Mathematical Modeling, GNN, Reinforcement Learning

Spanish (native), English (Fluent), German (A1)



Updated: 25th August 2022